Inventory of the Willbur Fisk Papers: Correspondence from Wilbur Fisk (Alphabetical), 1812 - 1839
Willbur Fisk Papers: Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Alphabetical), 1812 - 1839
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Fisk, Willbur.
1000-91
4.0
8
Willbur Fisk (1792-1839) was a Methodist minister and the first president of Wesleyan University.
Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Alphabetical) contains a complete alphabetical list of the recipients of letters from Willbur Fisk, including date ranges and numbers of letters. For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Materials collected by the college library in the 19th century.
Biographical Note
Willbur Fisk, Wesleyan’s first president, was born on 31 August 1792 and grew up in Brattleboro, Vermont. Although his mother feared that godlessness and sin in schools and colleges would make Fisk too worldly and strangle the spiritual life, Fisk graduated from Brown University in 1815, after also attending Peacham Academy and the University of Vermont. Surprisingly, given his future role at Wesleyan, Fisk was not initially drawn to the Methodist ministry following school. In fact, he struggled with his spiritual purpose at that time, working in law and as a tutor. However, a revelation during a bout of illness brought him to the ministry in 1818, and he devoted the rest of his life to his work as a Methodist. In 1825, Fisk was appointed principal of Wesleyan Academy in Wilbraham, Massachusetts, a preparatory school from which many Wesleyan University students were to be drawn.
When the decision to found a university in Middletown, Connecticut was made, Fisk was tapped for the role of first president. In his inaugural speech in 1831, he outlined his vision for the university, encapsulated by the statement that Education should be directed in reference to two objects—the good of the individual educated and the good of the world. Fisk was deeply involved in the administrative and curricular decisions of Wesleyan, and raised funds for the new college. He traveled to Europe to study educational institutions and collect scientific equipment in 1835-1836, and also took that time as a break from the stresses of the presidency. Suffering from ill-health his entire life, Fisk finally succumbed on 22 February 1839 while still serving as president.
Collection Overview
Correspondence from Willbur Fisk contains letters sent by Fisk to others, arranged in alphabetical order by sender's name. For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Alphabetical)
  For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
  The number in parentheses indicates the number of letters from that particular correspondent in the collection.
  - Adams, J. F., 31 July 1829 (1)
  - Allton, Mary Fisk, 16 May 1813-15 August 1838 (19)
  - Allton, Oren, 13 September 1832-19 September 1837 (2)
  - Archibald, Henry, 4 December 1828 (1)
  - Bangs, Nathan, 7 December 1827-30 December 1834 (5)
  - Barrus, Rufus, 20 November 1821 (1)
  - Bidwell, Ira M., 25 October 1833 (1)
  - Bragdon, Charles P., 15 January 1838 (1)
  - Brayton, Daniel, 23 February 1829-10 January 1838 (3)
  - Brewer, Susan, 10 August 1831 (1)
  - Britt, Benj. W., 25 October 1837 (1)
  - Brown, Charles L., 24 June 1833 (1)
  - Brown, W. C., 1837 (1)
  - Buckley, Samuel B., 30 August 1837 (1)
  - Bunting, J., DD., 4 November 1834-12 February 1836 (2)
  - Cahoon, G., 12 February 1818 (1)
  - Canfield, Mr., 20 November 1827 (1)
  - Clark, William, 2 April 1830-24 April 1830 (2)
  - Clergyman, A, 15 April 1838 (1)
  - Collins, Charles, 8 January 1838-4 August 1838 (3)
  - Deming, Benj. F., 9 August 1814-25 April 1834 (8)
  - Deming, Eunice, 6 August 1834 (1)
  - Dickinson, Austin, 6 April 1829 (1)
  - Eddy, Mr., 14 March 1828 (1)
  - Editors of the Christian Advocate, 11 September 1837-24 January 1839 (4)
    See also Sam. Luckey.
  - Families at Wilbraham, 4 June 1830 (1)
  - Filmore, Daniel, 18 August 1820-17 October 1838 (6)
  - Fisk, Hannah, 3 September 1828-3 January 1833 (2)
  - Fisk, Isaiah, 18 June 1816-16 July 1838 (15)
  - Fisk, Martha, 14 February 1836 (1)
  - Fisk, Mary
    See Allton, Mary Fisk.
  - Fisk, Ruth
    See Ruth Peck.
  - Foster, John, 4 December 1828 (1)
  - Gould, David, 13 May 1816-15 March 1817 (2)
  - Holdich, Prof. Joseph, 26 March 1820-16 December 1831 (2)
  - Hoyt, Benj. R., 29 September 1818 (1)
  - Hurlbut, Mary, 1 May 1836 (1)
  - Jackson, E., 26 April 1834 (1)
  - Johnstone, John, 4 August 1835-21 May 1836 (2)
  - Jones, Benj., 5 March 1829 (1)
  - Keener, Christian, 19 June 1834 (1)
  - Knowlton, Marcia, 24 March 1828-8 April 1838 (6)
    See also Marcia Palmer.
  - Lathrop, Seth, 7 March 1829 (1)
  - Lindsey, John, 17 December 1823-8 October 1830 (5)
  - Love, Bishop, 9 May 1828 (1)
  - Luckey, Samuel, 1 September 1827-24 January 1839 (21)
    See also Editors of the Christian Advocate.
  - Mattison, Spencer, 26 April 1834 (1)
  - Palmer, Marcia, 30 May 1813-9 September 1817 (5)
    See also Marcia Knowlton.
  - Palmer, Marcy, 15 May 1816-19 May 1837 (15)
  - Peck, Lydia, 7 September 1835-23 November 1836 (6)
  - Peck, Phinehas, 8 November 1812-9 January 1822 (5)
  - Peck, Ruth (Fisk), 29 June 1816-3 December 1838 (67)
  - Peterson, John, 6 February 1829 (1)
  - Phipps, Mary, 30 April 1823 (1)
  - Round, George, 12 January 1835 (1)
  - Ryerson, Egerton, 30 March 1829 (1)
  - Sandford, P. P., 6 November 1828 (1)
  - Scott, Harvey, 13 June 1818-26 September 1818 (2)
  - Scott, Orange, 7 February 1830 (1)
  - Smith, Augustus W., 1831-25 November 1836 (10)
  - Stewart, Prof., 1837 (1)
  - Sunderland, La Roy, 30 June 1835-10 January 1837 (3)
  - Taft, George, 22 April 1819 (1)
  - True, Charles K., 29 August 1830-6 July 1835 (3)
  - Whedon, Daniel D., 24 January 1833 (1)
  - Unknown correspondents, 23 May 1820-November 1836 (4)